David A. Rothrock Papers, 1885-1910. C33
Indiana University Archives
David A. Rothrock papers
1885-1910
Indiana University Archives
Rothrock, David A. (David Andrew), 1864-1949
C33
2.4 cubic feet
David Andrew Rothrock was a professor of mathematics at Indiana University from 1892 to 1937 and Director of Admissions from 1937-1938. The collection consists of manuscripts of published materials, teaching materials, notebooks kept while he was a student at the University of Chicago and Leipzig University, and one piece of correspondence The teaching materials include mathematical computations and exercises, writings about theories, notes from specific classes he taught, and student papers from a seminar.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Born in Milltown, Indiana in 1864, David Andrew Rothrock graduated from the Northern Indiana Normal School in 1887. From 1881 to 1891, he was a teacher and principal in Indiana and Illinois schools. Rothrock received his AB in 1892 and his AM in 1893 from Indiana University. In 1892, he joined Indiana University's faculty as an instructor in the Mathematics Department. Serving as an assistant professor from 1895 to 1900, Rothrock continued his mathematical studies at the University of Chicago (1894-1895 and the summer of 1896) and the University of Leipzig (Germany), where he received his Ph.D in 1898.
As a professor in the Mathematics Department from 1895 to 1937, Rothrock was the author of textbooks for high school and college students, as well as a contributor to professional journals. In addition to his work in mathematics, Rothrock became the Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences in 1920. In 1937, he resigned as Dean and Professor and served as the Director of Admissions for the 1937-1938 academic year. Retiring in 1938, Rothrock was named Professor Emeritus of Mathematics, a title he held until his death in 1949. Except for the time he spent studying at the Universities of Chicago and Leipzig, and a summer he spent as professor of Mathematics at the West Michigan Normal School, David Andrew Rothrock served Indiana University continuously from graduation until retirement.
Besides being a member of various mathematical societies, Rothrock served on the Bloomington City Council from 1918 to 1926, and as a member of the Indiana Legislature in 1919 and 1920. He also served on the State Conservation Committee from 1925 to 1933.
David Andrew Rothrock was the author of Invariants of the Finite Continuous Groups of the Plane (1899); Essentials of Algebra for Secondary Schools (1904); Supplementary Examples in Algebra (1906); Essentials in High School Mathematics: A Synopsis (1907); Solid Geometry(1909); Plane and Spherical Trigonometry (1910); Mathematical Tables (1910); Logarithmic, Trigonometric and Other Tables (1914); and High School Algebra (1928).
The David A. Rothrock Scholarships in Mathematics were established in 1956 through a gift to the Indiana University Foundation by Everett Antrim, a 1905 graduate who was a former student of Professor Rothrock.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of David Andrew Rothrock comprise 2.4 cubic feet. The collection is organized into four series: Publications, Teaching and Research Materials, Student Materials, and Correspondence.
The Publications series consists of manuscripts of published materials and sometimes copies of the publications. They are organized in 7 subseries: (1) Algebra Manuscript and Notes on Functions, (2) Concerning Differential Invariants and Conjugate Functions, (3) Elements of Plane and Spherical Trigonometry, (4) Essentials of Algebra, (5) Essentials of High School Mathematics, (6) Invariants of the Finite Continuous Groups of the Plane, and (7) Solid Geometry. Items in the subseries are arranged according to the original processing arrangement. It is not clear what "Algebra Manuscript and Notes on Functions" is a draft of; however, the materials appear to have been received together under that designation and the arrangement appears to maintain the original. "Concerning Differential Invariants" and "Conjugate Functions" are separate items that were published together. "Essentials of Plane and Spherical Trigonometry" may be a revision since some of the handwritten manuscript pages contain printed clippings. There are both a handwritten and typewritten manuscript as well as a file of figures and one that appears to be lesson plans for a one hour credit course. "Invariants of the Finite Continuous Groups of the Plane" was published in 1899. Rothrock's dissertation had the same title; however, the publication varies from the dissertation.
The Teaching and Research Materials series consists of three subseries: General, Teaching Materials, and Exercises. All of the items in the General subseries are undated and thus it is not clear whether items were teaching and research materials from when he was a student or faculty. A few items appear to be copies of the work of others. Materials in the General subseries are arranged alphabetically by title. The Teaching Materials subseries are dated material and can be identified as related to Rothrock's teaching. Items are arranged by date. The Exercises subseries contain undated mathematical exercises or computations that have little or no text. Materials in this subseries are arranged by title.
The Student Series contains materials that can be identified, by date, from his studies at the University of Chicago and the University of Leipzig. Three of the items are notebooks on Sophus Lie's (1842-1899) theories of continuous groups and differential equations. It is not clear whether these notebooks are a copy of a publication by Lie or whether they contain lecture notes. A fourth notebook contains lectures by Professor H. Maschke. Also in this subseries is Rothrock's 1898 dissertation.
The Correspondence series consists of one item, a letter to the Monroe County Board of Commissioners regarding a "view out and survey" of a pike road in Bean Blossom Township. A blank page at the end has this title on the verso: Viewers Report on Wayport and Mt. Tabor Pike Road. A date in the letter suggests it was written in 1906.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in four series: Publications, Teaching and Research Materials, Student Materials, and Correspondence.
Acquisition Information
Accession 0229.
Accession 2003/011. Theory of Functions, 1904 (Lithographed copy) donated by Evelyn Wilson.
Mathematics --Research.; Mathematics --Study and teaching (Higher).; Mathematics teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Mathematics teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Mathematicians --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Mathematicians --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Invariants of the finite continuous groups of the plane.; Essentials of algebra.; Indiana University -- Faculty -- Archives; Indiana University -- Faculty -- Correspondence; Universität Leipzig (1409-1953) -- students -- Archives; University of Chicago -- students -- Archives; Monroe County (Ind.). Commissioners -- Correspondence; Rothrock, David A. (David Andrew), 1864-1949 -- Archives; Rothrock, David A. (David Andrew), 1864-1949 -- Correspondence; Rothrock, David A. (David Andrew), 1864-1949 -- Invariants of the finite continuous groups of the plane; Rothrock, David A. (David Andrew), 1864-1949 -- Essentials of algebra
- Publications, 1904-1907; undated (Box 1)
  - Algebra Manuscripts and Notes on Functions, undated
    General
    It is not clear that this is a manuscript of a publication: however, it was originally processed as "Algebra Manuscripts and Notes on Functions," implying that it was a manuscript for publication. Files are arranged in the original processing order.
    - Notes on Calculus and Function Theory., Undated. (Box 1)
    - Untitled (equations)., Undated. (Box 1)
      Begins with equations.
    - Differential Calculus., Undated. (Box 1)
      Although this came with the Algebra Manuscripts and Notes on Functions, this may be a handwritten copy of part of Joseph Edwards' Differential Calculus, published by Macmillan in 1886.
    - Function Theory., Undated. (Box 1)
    - Untitled (If f (y) is even)., Undated. (Box 1)
      Begins with page 2: If f (y) is even.
  - Concerning Differential Invariants; Conjugate Functions and Canonical Transformations, 1906
    - Concerning Differential Invariants; Conjugate Functions and Canonical Transformations., 1906 (Box 1)
      Handwritten manuscript of each.
    - Concerning Differential Invariants; Conjugate Functions and Canonical Transformations., 1906 (Box 1)
      Offprint: Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science 1906:1-12.
  - Essentials in High School Mathematics., 1907?
    - Essentials in High School Mathematics. Typewritten ms., Undated. (Box 1)
      Typewritten with handwritten changes.
    - Essentials in High School Mathematics: A Synopsis., 1907 (Box 1)
      Offprint?
  - Essentials of Algebra., 1904?
    - Chapter 1. Introduction., Undated. (Box 1)
      Handwritten.
    - Multiplication., Undated. (Box 1)
    - Division., Undated. (Box 1)
    - Simple Equations; Fractional in Form., Undated. (Box 1)
    - Typewritten Manuscript., Undated. (Box 1)
  - Essentials of Plane and Spherical Trigonometry., Undated.
    May be the manuscript for a revision of his Essentials of Plane and Spherical Trigonometry first published in 1910 and again in 1925 and 1926. Contains clippings of printed materials.
    - Trigonometry., Undated. (Box 1)
    - Trigonometry., Undated. (Box 1)
      Typed.
    - Figures., Undated. (Box 1)
    - Spherical Trigonometry., Undated. (Box 1)
      Handwritten. Appears to be lesson plans for a one-hour credit course. References are to Rothwold text.
  - Invariants of the Finite Continuous Groups of the Plane., 1899 (Box 1)
    Indianapolis: Printed by Wm. B. Burford, 1899.
  - Solid Geometry, 1909 (Box 1)
    Handwritten. 2 copies.
- Teaching and Research Materials, 1895-1909; Undated.
  - General., Undated. (Box 2)
    - Address., Undated. (Box 2)
      Handwritten. Addresses the "very distinct kinds of training afforded young people by the colleges and universities of the present day": scholarship (research) and training in the classics.
    - Bessel Functions., Undated. (Box 2)
      Handwritten. "Resume of Winter Term."
    - Calculus of Variations., Undated. (Box 2)
      Handwritten. Has calculations inserted.
    - The Circle Squared by Theodore Heisel., Undated. (Box 2)
      Handwritten. Appears to be a copy of part of one of Carl Theodore Heisel's works on circle squaring.
    - Histories of Mathematics., Undated. (Box 2)
      Handwritten. Includes a time line.
    - Indiana University Faculty Survey., Undated. (Box 2)
      Handwritten. Includes list of professors and instructors at Indiana University from 1827-1907 and a survey of degrees later received by those who earned an AB and AM in Math from IU, up to 1908.
    - Lie's Differential Equations., Undated. (Box 2)
      Handwritten. Appears to be a manuscript about Lie's Differential Equations. Begins with page 3.
    - Modern Geometry., Undated. (Box 2)
    - Solution of Triangles in General., Undated. (Box 2)
      One copy is handwritten and typed and appears to be a draft. One copy is typed.
    - Theory of Functions of a Complex Variable., Undated. (Box 2)
    - Theory of Surfaces: Part II, Concerning Conicoids., Undated. (Box 2)
      Handwritten, mimeographed (?) copy.
    - Theory of Surfaces: Chapter I, Concerning Plane Sections of Conicoids., Undated. (Box 2)
      Handwritten. Oversize.
  - Teaching Materials, 1904-1906 (Box 3)
    - Theory of Functions Draft 1., 1904 (Box 3)
      Handwritten. Begins with "12. Rational Integral Functions."
    - Theory of Functions Draft 2., 1904 (Box 3)
      Handwritten. At head of page: "Introduction to the Theory of Functions of a Complete Variable."
    - Theory of Functions Draft 3., 1904 (Box 3)
      Handwritten. Begins: "Introductory Remarks."
    - Theory of Functions Lithographed version., 1904 (Box 3)
      Title page: Theory of Functions: Lectures, Winter and Spring Terms 1904, Indiana University. München: Lith. Anst. Hubert Köhler. 2 copies.
    - Differential Equations. Winter Term, 1905 (Box 3)
    - Function Theory., 1905 (Box 3)
      Handwritten. Winter Term, 1905.
    - Mathematical Seminary: A Partial Synopsis of Reports Given in Course 28. Winter Term., 1905-1906 (Box 3)
      Handwritten. Papers are bound into a notebook.
  - Exercises., Undated.
    - Behavior of R(z)., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Elliptic Harmonic Motion., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Ex. Forced Vibration., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Examples., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Form Diagonals., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Infinite Products., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Maxima & Minima., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Motion of an Incompressible Fluid in a Plane., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Particular Motions of a Point., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Solution of Right Triangles, Exercises., Undated. (Box 3)
      Typewritten. 2 copies.
    - Triple Series., Undated. (Box 3)
    - Trig., Undated. (Box 3)
      Handwritten. Begins with page 2.
- Student Materials, 1895-1898 (Box 4)
  - Elliptic Functions., 1895 (Box 4)
    Notebook. Notes of lectures by Professor H. Maschke, Winter 1895.
  - Lie's Differential Equations, no. 1., 1896 (Box 4)
    Handwritten. Notebook. On cover: University of Chicago, July 1, 1896 to July 15, 1896. Appears to a be a copy of Lie's book.
  - Lie's Differential Equations, no. 2., 1896 (Box 4)
    Handwritten. Notebook. On cover: Summer Quarter, July 16, 1896.
  - Notes on Lie's Continuous Groups., 1897 (Box 4)
    Handwritten. Notebook. Inside: Continuous Groups: Lie. Liepzig. 1897.
  - Invariants of the Finite Continuous groups of the Plane: Inaugural Dissertation., 1898 (Box 4)
    Handwritten. Bound.
- Correspondence.
  - Viewers Report on Wayport and Mt. Tabor Pike Road., 1906? (Box 4)
    Letter to the Board of Commissioners of Monroe County, Indiana. 4 copies: 1 typed, 2 handwritten, 1 mimeographed.